# Josue Baeza, PhD

University of Pennsylvania

☐ 817-980-7281

☐ baeza@pennmedicine.upenn.edu

in baezaj

baezaj83

☐ baezaj

Postdoctoral Fellow

# Summary

Postdoctoral research fellow developing mass spectrometry-based proteomics methods for studying biological systems. My postdoctoral research is aimed at understanding biochemical mechanisms of protein homeostasis with a major focus on the study of protein turnover during fetal development.

#### Education

2011–2017 **Ph.D.**, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI.

- o Mechanisms of mitochondrial protein acetylation
- o PI: John M. Denu

2008–2010 B.S., University of Texas Permian Basin, Odessa, TX.

- o Purification of the human T-cell leukemia virus
- o PI: Tracie M. Gibson

## Research Experience

- 2017 Vice Provost Postdoctoral Fellow, Benjamin A. Garcia, University of Pennsylvania.
  - Investigating the cross talk between protein turnover and epigenetics
  - Quantifying histone post-translational modifications in health and disease
  - Developing mass spectrometry-based proteomics technologies
  - o Developing computational tools for mass spectrometry
- 2011–2017 **Graduate Research Assistant**, *John M. Denu*, University of Wisconsin-Madison.
  - o Thesis aimed at understanding the mechanisms of mitochondrial protein acetylation
  - Developed a mass spectrometry-based method to quantify lysine acetylation stoichiometry
  - Coupled in vitro biochemistry methods with high resolution mass spectrometry technologies
  - o Determined second order rate constants for non-enzymatic acetylation
  - 2011 INRO Postbaccalaureate Research Fellow, Shyam Kottilil, National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases.
    - Determining genetic diversity of HCV genes in response to therapy
  - 2010 INRO Summer Internship Research Fellow, Shyam Kottilil, National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases.
    - o Determined cytokine gene expression in HIV/HCV coinfection cell system

- 2008–2010 **Undergraduate Research Assistant**, *Tracie M. Gibson*, University of Texas Permian Basin.
  - o Applied biochemical techniques to purify the human T-cell leukemia virus (HTLV)

#### Awards and Honors

- Jun 2019 ASMS Postdoctoral Career Development Award. American Society for Mass Spectrometry
- May 2018 May Institute Computation and Statistics for Mass Spectrometry and Proteomics.

  May Institute
- Apr 2017 UPenn Vice Provost Postdoctoral Fellowship for Academic Diversity. University of Pennsylvania
- Jan 2015 AAAS/Science Program for Excellence in Science. University of Wisconsin-Madison
- Jun 2014 Journal of Biological Chemistry (JBC) Author Profile. Journal of Biological Chemistry
- Jun 2014 Dept of Biological Chemistry Travel Award. University of Wisconsin-Madison
- Jun 2012 National Science Foundation (NSF) Graduate Research Fellowship (GRFP).
  National Science Foundation
- Jan 2012 Honorable Mention The Why Files Cool Science Image http://tinyurl.com/NeuroFlare. University of Wisconsin-Madison
- Aug 2011 Molecular Biosciences Training Grant (NIH T32). University of Wisconsin-Madison
- Aug 2011 Science and Medicine Graduate Research Scholars Fellowship (SciMed GRS). University of Wisconsin-Madison
- Apr 2010 Xi Zeta Chapter Gamma Sigma Epsilon Chemistry Honor Society. University of Texas Permian Basin
- Feb 2010 National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID) Intramural Research Opportunities (INRO). National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases
- Jun 2009 University of Texas Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (UT-LSAMP) Summer Research Academy. University of Texas Permian Basin

#### Teaching

- 2019 Epigenetics, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA.
  - Guest Lecturer
  - Mass spectrometry analysis of histone proteins
- 2019 Intro to R workshops, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA.
  - Intro to R: Data wrangling and visualization
  - Ongoing workshops teaching basic R

- 2017–2019 Introduction of Mass Spectrometry Based Proteomics, *UPenn Epigenetics Institute*, Philadelphia, PA.
  - o Annual workshops organized by UPenn Epigenetics Institute
  - Teaching fundamentals of mass spectrometry
- 2017–2019 Applied Proteomics, UPenn Epigenetics Institute, Philadelphia, PA.
  - o Second series of workshops hosted by the Epigenetics Institute
  - o overview of quantitative mass spectrometry
  - o Experimental design and statistics
  - 2014 Introduction to Human Biochemistry (TA), University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI.
    - o organized tutoring sessions for pre-medical undergraduate students
  - 2013 Human Biochemistry (TA), University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI.
    - o organized tutoring sessions for pre-medical undergraduate students
  - 2009 General Biology (TA), University of Texas Permian Basin, Odessa, TX.
    - o Biol 1307
    - o Teaching assistant for freshman biology students
  - 2009 General Chemistry (TA), University of Texas Permian Basin, Odessa, TX.
    - o Chem 1312
    - Teaching assistant for freshman chemistry students
  - 2008 Chemistry (TA), Odessa College, Odessa, TX.
    - Teaching assistant for chemistry students
  - 2008 Advancement Via Individual Determination, Odessa High School, Odessa, TX.
    - AVID tutor for high school students

## **Publications**

- 2020 Revealing dynamic protein acetylation across subcellular compartments, Josue Baeza, Alexis J Lawton, Jing Fan, Michael J Smallegan, Ian Lienert, Tejas Gandhi, Oliver M Bernhardt, Lukas Reiter, John M Denu, Journal of Proteome Research.
- 2020 Improved SILAC quantification with data independent acquisition to investigate bortezomib-induced protein degradation, Lindsay K Pino, Josue Baeza, Richard Lauman, Birgit Schilling, Benjamin A Garcia, bioRxiv.
- 2020 Sex-specific effects of in vitro fertilization on adult metabolic phenotypes and hepatic transcriptomic and proteomic pathways in mouse., Marisa S Bartolomei, Laren Narapareddy, Richard M Schultz, Benjamin A Garcia, Eric Rhon-Calderon, Lisa A Vrooman, Duy Nguyen, Josue Baeza, Yemin Lan, bioRxiv.

- 2019 The E3 ligase adaptor molecule SPOP regulates fetal hemoglobin levels in adult erythroid cells, Xianjiang Lan, Eugene Khandros, Peng Huang, Scott A Peslak, Saurabh K Bhardwaj, Jeremy D Grevet, Osheiza Abdulmalik, Hongxin Wang, Cheryl A Keller, Belinda Giardine, Josue Baeza, Emily R Duffner, Osama El Demerdash, Xiaoli S Wu, Christopher R Vakoc, Benjamin A Garcia, Ross C Hardison, Junwei Shi, Gerd A Blobel, Blood advances.
- 2019 Deep profiling and custom databases improve detection of proteoforms generated by alternative splicing, Laura M Agosto, Matthew R Gazzara, Caleb M Radens, Simone Sidoli, Josue Baeza, Benjamin A Garcia, Kristen W Lynch, Genome research.
- 2019 Site-Specific Lysine Acetylation Stoichiometry Across Subcellular Compartments, Anastasia J Lindahl, Alexis J Lawton, Josue Baeza, James A Dowell, John M Denu, Protein Acetylation.
- 2018 Dynamic acetylation of phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase toggles enzyme activity between gluconeogenic and anaplerotic reactions, Pedro Latorre-Muro, Josue Baeza, Eric A Armstrong, Ramon Hurtado-Guerrero, Francisco Corzana, Lindsay E Wu, David A Sinclair, Pascual Lopez-Buesa, Jose A Carrodeguas, John M Denu, Molecular cell.
- 2018 Quantifying dynamic protein acetylation using quantitative stoichiometry, Josue Baeza, Alexis J Lawton, Jing Fan, Michael J Smallegan, Ian Lienert, Tejas Gandhi, Oliver M Bernhardt, Lukas Reiter, John M Denu, bioRxiv.
- 2016 Mechanisms and dynamics of protein acetylation in mitochondria, Josue Baeza, Michael J Smallegan, John M Denu, Trends in biochemical sciences.
- 2016 Investigating histone acetylation stoichiometry and turnover rate, J Fan, J Baeza, JM Denu, Methods in enzymology.
- 2015 Site-specific reactivity of nonenzymatic lysine acetylation, Josue Baeza, Michael J Smallegan, John M Denu, ACS chemical biology.
- 2014 Stoichiometry of site-specific lysine acetylation in an entire proteome, Josue Baeza, James A Dowell, Michael J Smallegan, Jing Fan, Daniel Amador-Noguez, Zia Khan, John M Denu, Journal of Biological Chemistry.

- 2013 Activation of the protein deacetylase SIRT6 by long-chain fatty acids and widespread deacylation by mammalian sirtuins, Jessica L Feldman, Josue Baeza, John M Denu, Journal of Biological Chemistry.
- 2012 Rapid identification of ESKAPE bacterial strains using an autonomous microfluidic device, Jack Y Ho, Nate J Cira, John A Crooks, Josue Baeza, Douglas B Weibel, PloS one.
- 2012 Human immunodeficiency virus enhances hepatitis C virus replication by differential regulation of IFN and TGF family genes, Xiaozhen Zhang, Marybeth Daucher, Josue Baeza, Cheol-Woo Kim, Rodney Russell, Shyamasundaran Kottilil, Journal of medical virology.

### Research Talks

- Jun 2020 Applications of Skyline for Method Development and Quantification of Histone PTMs, Skyline User Group Meeting, Online.
- Jun 2019 Quantitative analysis of the fetal tissue 'Translatome' reveals temporal and tissue-specific regulatory networks in utero, American Society for Mass Spectrometry, Atlanta, GA.
- Mar 2018 Quantifying protein synthesis rates during fetal development reveals temporal and tissue specific regulatory networks, *US Human Proteome Organization*, Minneapolis, MN.

#### Selected Posters

- Oct 2020 A robust and flexible method for quantifying protein turnover rates across an entire proteome, US Human Proteome Organization Connect, Online.
- Mar 2019 Quantitative analysis of the fetal tissue translatome by mass spectrometry reveals temporal and tissue-specific regulatory networks in utero, US Human Proteome Organization, Washington DC.
- Sep 2018 Quantifying the fetal tissue translatome reveals temporal and tissue specific regulatory networks during development, Human Proteome Organization, Orlando, FL.
- Jun 2017 Acetylation stoichiometry analysis of the Sirt3 deficient liver, American Society for Mass Spectrometry, San Antonio, TX.

- Jun 2015 Site specific reactivity of non-enzymatic lysine acetylation, American Society for Mass Spectrometry, St. Louis, MO.
- Dec 2014 Site specific reactivity of non-enzymatic lysine acetylation, American Society for Cell Biology, Philadelphia, PA.
- Jun 2014 Stoichiometry of acetylation in an entire proteome, American Society for Mass Spectrometry, Minneapolis, MN.
- Aug 2013 Stoichiometry of acetylation determined by isotopic modification and mass spectrometry, Molecular Biosciences Training Grant Retreat, Madison, WI.
- Sep 2011 MicroRNA expression profiling identifies potential anti-viral targets in HCV-infected human hepatoma cells, International Symposium on Hepatitis C Virus, Seattle, WA.
- Aug 2010 Determining hepatitis C virus diversity and evolution during antiviral therapy using quantitative deep sequencing, NIH Summer Research Program Poster Day, Bethesda, MD.
- Feb 2010 Purification of the human T-cell leukemia virus type-1 virion using sucrose density gradient ultracentrifugation, American Association for the Advancement of Science, San Diego, CA.

## — Professional Organizations

- 2017 Human Proteome Organization.
- 2017 US Human Proteome Organization.
- 2013 American Society for Mass Spectrometry.